<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-19T11:26:37+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Superpowered Memory</title><subtitle>How To Master Your Memory And Become an Effective Learner</subtitle><author><name>João Eira</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Biases That Stop You From Becoming An Effective Learner</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/biases-that-stop-effective-learning" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Biases That Stop You From Becoming An Effective Learner" /><published>2017-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/biasesforesighthindsight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/biases-that-stop-effective-learning">&lt;p&gt;How many times has it happened to you that the grade of an exam you had thought you aced comes back lower than you were expecting? You were so sure you had done a great job that you’re sure the teacher must have gotten it wrong. She just didn’t understand what you were trying to say. You go to her office to ask if you could take a look at the exam to see what you’re grade was so low. She searches for the exam and hands it over to you. You start reading what you wrote for one of the answers, which, embarrassingly,  is marked all over in red, a bad sign, yet you can’t tell what’s wrong with it. You ask her if she could explain what was it got wrong and, after she does, it hits you just how dumb you were. It was so obvious! How could have you gotten it wrong? Just the day before you’d been going through your notes on this. It must have been a fluke! The only reason you’d gotten it wrong was because of some weird inexplicable reason that made it so that you didn’t remember the right answer! It must have been it, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We humans are easily misled. That’s an uncontroversial statement by itself, we’ve all been wrong or made a mistake some way or another, but what I mean by this is that not only are we often mistaken, but we are also blind to shoe same mistakes. Take the Linda Problem, created by Amos Tversky and Daniel Kahneman to show how easy it is to trip up our reasoning skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linda is 31 years old, single, outspoken, and very bright. She majored in philosophy. As a student, she was deeply concerned with issues of discrimination and social justice, and also participated in anti-nuclear demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is more probable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1----linda-is-a-bank-teller&quot;&gt;1 -  Linda is a bank teller&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2----linda-is-a-bank-teller-and-is-active-in-the-feminist-movement&quot;&gt;2 -  Linda is a bank teller and is active in the feminist movement.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would you answer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you chose option 2, you’ll be surprised to know that that’s not the right answer, but don’t worry, most people make the same mistake. Why is option 2 incorrect? Recall that both options 1 and 2 include the possibility that Linda is a bank teller but only option 2 introduces a further restriction, that of Linda being active in the feminist movement, meaning that if 2 is true then 1 is also true , but not the other way around. Thus, the more probable option is the option 1. This type of mistake is called the conjunction fallacy, when we assume that a specific condition is more probable than a more general one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What tends to happen is that people cling on to the information provided, making judgments about the type of person Linda is and bringing those judgments with them when evaluating which option is more probable when that knowledge is at best circumstantial to the question asked. Stephen Jay Gould, the eminent biologist, was to say &lt;em&gt;“I am particularly fond of this example because I know that the [conjoint] statement is least probable, yet a little homunculus in my head continues to jump up and down, shouting at me—“but she can’t just be a bank teller; read the description.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is just a single example of the types of mistakes we often make, but a quick glimpse at the extent of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases&quot;&gt;list of cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt; that plague our thinking and decision making should make clear the extent of the problem we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our goal is to &lt;a href=&quot;http://superpoweredmemory.com/becoming-an-effective-leaner&quot;&gt;become effective learners&lt;/a&gt;, then we must learn what sort of biases are likely to rear their head when we’re trying to learn something new so that we can find ways to neutralize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main way that biases can affect us our learning is by impairing our judgments of whether we have actually learned something or not. Think back to that initial exam example. First there was this sense that you must have gotten the answer right, you were sure of it, but once shown you were wrong and what you should have answered instead, you thought you knew it all along! That can’t possibly be the case or you would have answered correctly in the first place. Something must have happened that impeded you to judge correctly whether you knew something, making you overconfident in your judgment that you knew it when you didn’t. Then, further compounding on that misjudgment, when the teacher told you what the correct answer was you inferred that you knew it all along! This is another misjudgment since it’s highly unlikely that just because you were shown the correct answer you will recall it again when you need it again, maybe in a future exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a variety of possible biases that can creep up on us when we’re trying to learn something new but there are two big ones that you must always be on alert to make sure you don’t follow into a trap: the hindsight and foresight biases, or the “I-knew-it-all-along” tendency and the “I-will-know-it-in-the-future” tendency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hindsight bias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindsight bias refers to the tendency we have, once information is made available to us, to think that we knew it all along. We’ve all fallen prey to this bias. An easy way to experience it is when we’re doing practice questions and we don’t quite know answer to one of them is, so we turn to the solutions and “Ah, of course! It was so obvious, I knew this.” This is what you made you so sure that you knew the correct answer to the question that you got wrong on the exam after the teacher told you what it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bias is a pernicious one, because it’s so easy to fall prey to even when you’re aware of it. It robs you of the subjective feeling of not knowing something, which we need, even if it’s unpleasant, because if we don’t have an accurate understanding of what we do and do not know we can’t allocate our precious time to those things we don’t know and, worse yet, we will think we know things we actually don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why you should always be on high alert to make sure you don’t fall prey hindsight bias, because it doesn’t allow you to make corrections to your learning since you never get to realize that something is wrong in the first place. If, prior to an event that triggers hindsight bias, your knowledge is at best shaky, hindsight bias will make it so that you judge that knowledge as certain, as something you know, when you in fact don’t. Because of this, you carry on thinking that you do not need to review your knowledge to correct any misunderstandings and so when you actually need that knowledge, say in an exam, you won’t have that knowledge to support you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Foresight bias&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If hindsight bias is the mistake of thinking one knew it all along, then foresight bias is the mistake of thinking we will know it in the future. Foresight bias stems from us being blind to the conditions that lead us to recall certain things in the first place. Let’s take an example. When you are studying something you often have a book with you, or some notes, along with that endless repository of knowledge called the Internet. You’re reading your notes, or the textbook, and you’re fairly certain you’ve got this covered. The material feels familiar to you which must mean you already know this. Because you don’t want to waste your time on things you already know, you switch to something where you’re a bit shakier. The problem arises when the time comes you need to use the knowledge and you find that you don’t know it as well as you thought you did. Your mistake was in thinking that because the material felt familiar to you it must have meant not only that you knew it well, but that you would continue to know it in the future, when in fact that feeling of familiarity wasn’t a good indicator of the actual state of your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foresight bias arises because the environment you’re in when you must call on that knowledge is oftentimes different from the one you studied it in. In an exam you no longer have access to your notebooks, your books, or the Internet. The room is different, the chair feels funny, and the table is written on with lewd comments from past students. Now you need to recall the material entirely from memory, and it suddenly feels like there’s a roadblock impeding you from accessing it, which sucks because you were so certain you knew that material but, for some reason, now you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is cue-based. When you’re learning something, you are creating new memories that are connected to certain cues based on your environment, or other knowledge that you associated them with. This means that if, for some reason, the cues to which those memories that you want to access are not present when you need them, say by going to an exam without your books, notebook, etc, then the likelihood of you accessing those memories is greatly impaired. As if your memories are like a door where the cues are keys that open it. If you don’t have the proper keys with you you can’t open the door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter foresight bias. This bias works by combining the performance heuristic with the shallow cues that are present when you’re studying. What happens is that when you’re studying all those cues are available to you, making it so that your memories are easily brought forth to mind. Because we equate recall performance with learning, we assume that we know, at a deep level, that material, when in fact that effortless recall is just due to those cues being available. This presents an issue because if you feel like you know something, you will stop wasting your time with it, but, if that judgment is misplaced, by not making the efforts to make sure you actually learn what you’re trying to learn, when the time comes that you need that knowledge, like in an exam, you won’t have it, and you will end up failing because of a trick your brain played on you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What can you do?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s so easy to fool ourselves into thinking we know things when we don’t, it would be helpful if there were techniques we could use so that we’re less vulnerable to those biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, there are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If hindsight bias works by making us mistake recognition for learning, then a way to make sure that our judgment of whether we know something or not is contingent on us actually knowing the material is to testing ourselves on it. Through testing ourselves we’re collapsing our judgment of whether we know something or not into a binary answer. Either we know something or we don’t. If we know it, testing will give us a more reliable judgment of it than mere recognition could and, if for some reason our knowledge is more flimsy than we previously thought, testing will make sure you know you don’t know the material as well as you thought you did. You will fail, and failure will unambiguously tell you what you need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By testing yourself you will also be working to create memory cues that aren’t incidental to the environment but that are internal instead. Because testing is more similar to the conditions in which you will need that knowledge, say on an exam, the likelihood of correct recall will be greater than if you don’t test yourself because the cues those memories are now linked to are cues that will be also be available on the exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice takeaway for you to take from this is that your judgments of whether you know something or not should be based on your performance on tasks that are more like those where you’re going to be needing that knowledge and not on your subjective experience when your studying. You are easily fooled, so if you base your decisions on whether to continue studying or not based on whether it “feels” like you know it or not you will most likely end up being wrong. Much better to make those decisions after testing yourself on that knowledge because then you will truly know if you know something.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>João Eira</name></author><summary type="html">How many times has it happened to you that the grade of an exam you had thought you aced comes back lower than you were expecting? You were so sure you had done a great job that you’re sure the teacher must have gotten it wrong. She just didn’t understand what you were trying to say. You go to her office to ask if you could take a look at the exam to see what you’re grade was so low. She searches for the exam and hands it over to you. You start reading what you wrote for one of the answers, which, embarrassingly,  is marked all over in red, a bad sign, yet you can’t tell what’s wrong with it. You ask her if she could explain what was it got wrong and, after she does, it hits you just how dumb you were. It was so obvious! How could have you gotten it wrong? Just the day before you’d been going through your notes on this. It must have been a fluke! The only reason you’d gotten it wrong was because of some weird inexplicable reason that made it so that you didn’t remember the right answer! It must have been it, right?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To Learn Something New, Make Things Hard On Yourself</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/make-things-hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Learn Something New, Make Things Hard On Yourself" /><published>2017-08-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/makingthingshard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/make-things-hard">&lt;p&gt;Everybody wants to take that one shortcut that will bypass all the hard work needed to reach their goals. Trying to learn a new language? I’m sure you’ll be able to find dozens of products in the Internet that will promise you fluency in under 2 hours. Or 1 hour. Or 30 minutes. There’s an entire line of books predicated on the idea that you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss_2?url=search-alias%3Dstripbooks&amp;amp;field-keywords=teach+yourself+24+hours&quot;&gt;learn a new programming language in 24 hours&lt;/a&gt;, which prompted legendary computer scientist &lt;a href=&quot;http://norvig.com/21-days.html&quot;&gt;Peter Norvig&lt;/a&gt; to write a response to this inane idea by proposing a tantalizing syllabus which, if you follow, will turn you into a good programmer in under 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not too much time, is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course people want shortcuts, why wouldn’t they? It’s only rational to want to get the same results in the shortest amount of time possible. We even have a name for this: efficiency. The trouble is, most people taking shortcuts in the name of efficiency end up working against their own goals. In their attempt to learn new things in such a short time they end up learning next to nothing. What usually happens is that despite some initial success, whatever it is that they’ve learn is quickly later forgotten. We’ve all crammed for some test, right? It somewhat works in that we’ve “learned” something for the test, but once we turn the test in it’s like a timer goes off in our heads that sweeps away all that crammed knowledge we worked so hard to get, never to be remembered again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is not getting around it. Learning is hard. In fact, Learning should be hard. Confused? Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For close to three decades now memory researchers have made the distinction between how accessible a memory is versus how well stored it is in your brain. You can quickly remember what you had yesterday for dinner since not much time has passed and you haven’t had dinner since, but it is unlikely that you’ll store that knowledge for much longer. What was it that you had for dinner two weeks ago? It doesn’t come as easily, if at all. Yet you do remember things well into the past, we all do. This means that memories can differ between one another based on their retrieval strength, a measure of how accessible they are, and their storage strength, a measure of their endurance in your brain. Cramming, for example, works by increasing the retrieval strength of memories at the cost of their storage strength, making it so that while we can recall those memories when the test arrives, we won’t be storing them for a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since our goal is to &lt;a href=&quot;http://superpoweredmemory.com/becoming-an-effective-leaner&quot;&gt;learn in a way that is effective&lt;/a&gt;, not to cram for some test and later forget everything, do you figure we would want our new memories to have high retrieval strength or high storage strength? Ideally we would want both to be strong. Being able to quickly recall something that is holding onto our brains by a thin thread is useless in the long run, which is what cramming ends up doing. Yet holding onto memories for a long time without being able to access them seems wasteful. Ideally, we would want a good mix of both, but as students we’re drawn towards increasing retrieval strength, that is, making things accessible, because we equate accessibility with learning. It’s a mental bias that we have ingrained in us, the idea that because knowledge comes easily it must mean that we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legendary learning researcher Robert Bjork has written many influential papers on this idea. He notes that, as learners, our goal is to learn something, to understand the relevant ideas and connections behind whatever it is that we want to learn and have that knowledge maintained in our long-term memory, ready to use when we need it. Yet during our learning process, instead of measuring success by the amount that we’re learning, which is hard to do introspectively, we use a metric that is much easier for us to access: performance. We routinely conflate short-term performance with long-term learning, thinking they’re one of the same when in fact they have almost nothing to do with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re sitting there, reading this article, and if I’ve done my job correctly, you’ve understood the points that I’ve made so far. “Interesting,” you say, “we conflate performance with learning. I didn’t know this before and now I do.” And there’s the bait and switch. Because you have made sense of what it is that the article is about while you were reading it you presume that from now you’ll continue to remember this new knowledge. This foresight bias, that we’ll know something in the future that we know now, is the core of the performance/learning dichotomy. Because we live in the present, while learning is something that happens in the long-term, we are not able to distinguish one from the other and so we take a mental shortcut, taking one to be the other. Since I know this now it means I’ll know it in the future. If it sounds hard to imagine that you haven’t learned anything from this article when you feel so certain that you have, think on how many articles you’ve read in your life and the percentage of them where you still remember what they were about, the points that they made, their arguments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why products selling quick and easy recipes to learn something new will forever be something we’ll have to live with. Not only do we want to learn new things as fast as possible, our very usage of those products, while only delivering short-term performance, will feel like long-term learning. “See this Mary, the Spanish word for dog is perro, I learned this in this book! I am so looking forward to my trip to Argentina next week, I’ll feel like a local speaking the language!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if there is no easy path to learning, and if we’re easily fooled into thinking we’re learning something when we aren’t, how do we go about actually learning something? Well, if by making things easy we’re fooling ourselves, one way to make sure we’re putting our time to good use is to make things harder. Yes, you’ve read that right. Harder. This is another idea put forth by Robert Bjork, that by making things hard on us, by introducing desirable difficulties, we’ll have much more success in learning something than if we do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s use an example. Let’s say you must learn the ideas within a scientific paper and you’ve already read the paper once. You’re not content with only reading the paper that one time however, maybe you don’t think you’ve quite grasped its finer points, so you decide that you’re learning journey is still not over. You figure you have two options: you can either read the paper one more time, perhaps discovering some connection you hadn’t notice before, or you could write a short freeform essay on what the paper is about. Which one would you choose? Most people would decide to read the paper one more time, and it’s likely that we would too. I know I have done this many times, even when I know it’s not a good use of my time. For starters, it’s just so much easier. Instead of writing something out the top of your head, all you have do is read. And it does feel like you’re getting something done, you really do notice something you hadn’t before, an idea that you hadn’t quite grasped, a connection you hadn’t yet made. Surely this means you’ve learned something new. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, but it’s highly unlikely and you probably will only be fooling yourself. Performance and learning aren’t the same thing. While you may have noticed something you hadn’t before, this does not translate into you knowing it in the future, when you need it for, say, an exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A much better strategy would have been to write an essay on what the paper is about. Sure, it’s hard. You’re feeling lazy and writing is mentally taxing. But again and again, what the research has demonstrated is that by recalling memories from your mind is a fantastic technique that improves how well those memories are stored. Consider the following study from Larsen, Butler, and Roediger. They wanted to investigate whether retrieval practice, i.e., testing a subject’s memory by having him complete an actual test, enhanced the long-term retention of medical information. They divided subjects into two groups that were to study material on neurological disorders, but one group would take a series of three short-answer tests on the material every two weeks while the other would study a review sheet in that same interval. After 6 months of this, a final test was given to both groups. Can you guess which group performed better on the final test? The one who did the tests! In fact, the difference in performance between both groups was almost one standard deviation, a sizeable difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The essay that you would write about the paper’s topic would be like a kind of test for you. Without any aids, you write as much as what you know about it without censuring yourself (there’s no grade in the end after all). Afterward, you compare what you wrote with what the paper actually said, and you can improve afterward by noticing slight differences between what you wrote and what the paper said, or by noticing that you left something out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that by introducing desirable difficulties in your studying methods you’ll achieve much better learning performance than just taking the easy way out. Sure, it’s harder than the alternative, but on the other hand, it’s how you’ll be able to achieve your own goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing why making things hard on yourself by introducing desirable difficulties will lead to more effective learning will help you devise and implement better learning strategies that will get you the results you want. Follow the ultimate learning adage, first coined by Robert Bjork: Input Less, Output More.  Spend more of your time producing content rather than consuming it. Write an essay on what you’re currently learning instead of spending yet more time going through your notes. It’s hard work but it pays off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>João Eira</name></author><summary type="html">Everybody wants to take that one shortcut that will bypass all the hard work needed to reach their goals. Trying to learn a new language? I’m sure you’ll be able to find dozens of products in the Internet that will promise you fluency in under 2 hours. Or 1 hour. Or 30 minutes. There’s an entire line of books predicated on the idea that you can learn a new programming language in 24 hours, which prompted legendary computer scientist Peter Norvig to write a response to this inane idea by proposing a tantalizing syllabus which, if you follow, will turn you into a good programmer in under 10 years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What You Need To Know To Become An Effective Learner</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/becoming-an-effective-leaner" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What You Need To Know To Become An Effective Learner" /><published>2017-08-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/effectiveleaner</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/becoming-an-effective-leaner">&lt;p&gt;Learning is a foundational aspect of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start early, entering formal education when we’re young, some only leaving decades later with a degree or more in their belt. After entering the workforce, we might be forgiven in thinking that our job will consist in nothing more than applying what we already know, that learning new things is at best a tangential task. Yet we are soon disabused of that idea when the reality of the modern workplace is thrust upon us. Things move fast. New technology is always being introduced, and old paradigms are always in danger of being replaced. We soon realize that we live in a world where we either continue updating our knowledge or find ourselves stuck in the same place, or worse, becoming obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may be exaggerating for effect, but the reality is not that far off. Think back to how the world was 5, 10, 20 years in the past and contrast it to today to see how much can change in so short a period. Can you be certain that your skills will continue to be relevant a decade from now? Or, if you’re still a student, do you think what you’ve learned so far will be enough to get you through the many decades still ahead of you? Probably not. Thus the need to make learning a habitual activity of ours. We must all become perpetual learners, or face the consequences.
There is an added difficulty to all of this however: Most people are terrible learners. It would perhaps be a rosier picture if the truth were that most people are mediocre learners, with some slightly better and some slightly worse, but that’s just not what’s happening. Again and again, what research has found is that people, for the most part, are terrible learners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would think, given that we start school so young and must continue to learn new things throughout our lives in some shape or form that we would know how to study in such a way as to promote efficient learning. Yet we are never taught how to study. &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/s13423-011-0181-y&quot;&gt;When asked by researchers&lt;/a&gt;, 65 to 80% of students answer “no” to the question “Do you study the way you do because somebody taught you to study that way?”. Whether the remaining 20 to 30% study in a way consistent to research findings on how to learn is a different question altogether. What often happens is that we pick up tips and tricks from our peers and use those techniques thinking they must be the best ways to learn. How could they not be if everyone is using them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet these crowdsourced strategies are so ineffective, and so widely used, that researchers have invariably concluded most of us are terrible learners. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev-psych-113011-143823&quot;&gt;As researchers Robert Bjork, John Dunlosky, and Nate Kornell put it&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;“there is in fact much that we, as learners, do not tend to know about how best to assess and manage our own learning.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse yet is that this ignorance isn’t easily corrected. One would think that decades spent learning and putting that knowledge to the quite literal test would make it so that bad learning practices would be left by the wayside, with only the good practices surviving the ordeal. Yes, other people might be using these techniques but once you yourself see that they aren’t getting you the results you want, one would think that you would switch to better techniques. That, however, does not tend to happen. The legions of students armed with nothing but highlighters in libraries worldwide, and the overwhelming evidence against their usage, is a testament to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are we to do then? If learning is so important, but we’re terrible at it, does this mean we’re screwed? Is there nothing that can be done? Thankfully, things aren’t so dire. There are general principles and techniques, identified after decades of scientific research on how to learn, that you can use to get much better results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the key principles you must know to become an effective learner:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-the-peculiarities-of-human-memory-and-learning&quot;&gt;a) The peculiarities of human memory and learning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;b-the-techniques-that-enhance-the-storage-and-retrieval-of-information-from-memory&quot;&gt;b) The techniques that enhance the storage and retrieval of information from memory&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;c-how-to-monitor-the-state-of-your-learning-and-the-myriad-ways-in-which-your-judgment-can-be-fooled&quot;&gt;c) How to monitor the state of your learning and the myriad ways in which your judgment can be fooled&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-peculiarities-of-human-memory&quot;&gt;The peculiarities of human memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first step in the quest to become effective learners is to understand what &lt;a href=&quot;https://bjorklab.psych.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/13/2016/07/RBjork_EBjork_1992.pdf&quot;&gt;Elizabeth and Robert Bjork&lt;/a&gt; call the “important peculiarities” of human memory. We need to know the way our memories store and retrieve new knowledge so that we can tailor our learning approach to one that enhances those processes.
Our memory doesn’t work like recording device. It is not the brain’s equivalent to a computer hard-drive as it doesn’t store information in our long-term memories by making a bit by bit copy of that information. Instead, it stores new information by its relationship with what we already know, growing stronger the more connections it can create. This means that, as a first approach, our learning process must become an active one where we tease out the relationships between what we’re learning with what we already know instead of taking notes and fervently praying that by some miraculous process they get imprinted in our mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important thing to know is that the retrieval of information from memory is not without its consequences. Remembering things changes our memories, oftentimes making those retrieved memories stronger. Retrieving information from memory works as a memory modifier, making that memory more recallable in the future, as if the brain figured out that since you selected this one memory against all others it means the information contained within it is important, making it more accessible for when you later need it. In practical terms, this means that making an effort to recall things, by testing yourself for example, will improve your memory in such a way as to make that recall much less effortful, ensuring that when time comes that you need it, in an exam for example, you have an easier time recalling all that knowledge you spent so much time learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remarkable thing, from an historical perspective, is that we’ve known about how our memories form long term memories for centuries now ever since Hermann Ebbinghaus made his initial experiments that established the scientific study of memory. Yet, unless you happen to take a course on memory in college, very few of us learn of any of this. My own course &lt;a href=&quot;superpoweredmemory.com&quot;&gt;Superpowered Memory&lt;/a&gt; is an attempt at rectifying this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;input-less-output-more&quot;&gt;Input less, Output More&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing how memory works doesn’t help if we continue to use suboptimal techniques that don’t take that knowledge into account. If our learning strategy continues to be reading the material and highlighting what we deem to be the important sections we will continue to be frustrated when we look back and realize we remember close to nothing. All those arduous hours laboring away in the library will have been for nothing. If we are to become effective learners, we need to leverage our understanding of how we form new memories into the techniques that promote the storage, and subsequent retrieval, of new information.
This means that, as effective leaners, we must eschew passive activities like re-reading and highlighting, and embrace active learning techniques such as deep processing and testing. Our studying will consist in sketching the connections between what we’re learning with what we already know, teasing away the similarities and the ways in which it differs from other things. Additionally, because our goal is to create lasting memories, we will put our notes and books away to test ourselves to see if we remember what it was we were studying. This will lead to much a much deeper understanding than merely re-reading your notes ever would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from understanding why certain techniques work better than others, to become effective learners we must also understand how to go about applying those techniques because all the knowledge in the world about how to learn won’t help us if we don’t know how to apply it. Knowing that spacing one’s studying sessions, say, throughout a semester, will lead to better and more durable understanding, compared with bunching them for the week right before the exam, will have implications regarding how we plan our studying. Furthermore, knowing that memory retrieval is dependent on the cues available from the environment will make it so that we will vary the environment we are studying to make sure the new memories we are forming are locked in with cues that aren’t available when we most need that knowledge, like in an exam.
As effective learners, we will make sure to follow the most important learning adage there is, originally coined by researcher Robert Bjork: Input Less, Output More!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-we-know-what-we-know&quot;&gt;Do we know what we know?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presumably, no one spends hours studying what they already know, but are our judgments of what we know or not know accurate? To become effective learners, we must also become efficient learners, making sure that our time is spent in such a way that learning is achieved and our efforts are not for nothing. Thus the need to make sure our judgments of whether we’ve learned something correspond to the degree to which learning has occurred. One would think that the only way it would feel like we know something would be because we actually know it, but the ways by which our judgments can be misled &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases&quot;&gt;are so many as to beggar belief&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are frequently overconfident, &lt;a href=&quot;http://superpoweredmemory.com/make-things-hard&quot;&gt;thinking we know something more than we in fact do&lt;/a&gt;, and the ineffective studying techniques that we mistakenly use further compound on that overconfidence. We equate performance based on fleeting circumstances, such has recalling something after just having read the material, with actual learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To become effective learners, we must understand that our judgments of learning are heuristics and are thus subject to systematic biases, such as hindsight bias, the feeling that we knew it all along, and foresight bias, the feeling that because we know it now we will know it in the future. Given our knowledge of these biases, we know not to trust our judgments too much unless they come from our performance in the activities that actually matter. Thus our extensive use of testing and generation, because the only accurate way of knowing if we know something is by actually demonstrating that we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an effective learner is not an easy task. It takes work to implement these techniques, and they’re often more mentally taxing than just re-reading things. Having to be on constant alert as to whether our judgments of learning are impaired by biases or not can be difficult as it means going against our own conscious experiences or feelings that we do know something. Yet given the increased importance of learning across the lifespan, that increased difficulty will pay of when you find yourself in a better situation than you would have been otherwise. These added difficulties are what will make sure that your goals are achieved, and hence the way to think about them is as an investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You put the work now so that the rewards can be reaped later.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>João Eira</name></author><summary type="html">Learning is a foundational aspect of our lives.</summary></entry></feed>
